Okay, today's דף daf is דף י״ג, Daf Yud Gimmel, we pick
up on י״ב עמוד ב׳. Yud Bet Amud Bet. We are in
the middle of a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the
חכמים Chachamim about a case where somebody said give this שטר שחרור
shtar shichrur to my slave, a writ of manumission, or גט get
to my wife, and the person by taking it can that be
considered like he's representing the wife or the slave and they are
automatically divorced as their שליח shaliach and automatically divorced or automatically free?
So that is not the case by the wife because there is
actually can be a downside to being divorced in that the husband
will no longer have a legal obligation to provide for her, but
the חכמים chachamim say but the case by the עבד, eved, he
is automatically freed because it's only a benefit to the slave to
be free, and therefore זכין לאדם שלא בפניו zachin l'adam shelo befanav
this person can represent the slave. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir responds back
and says it is not a benefit to the slave to be
free. Now why not? Well the first reason to think not is
because the master might have an obligation to feed his slave. But
to that the חכמים chachamim have already said in the משנה mishna
the master does not have a legal obligation to feed his slave,
to feed his slave, so clearly that's not a benefit that he's
losing out on. The discussion in the גמרא Gemara whether that technically
meant that or not, but anyway effectively that's what it means. And
now we're getting to the second point which is the issue of
תרומה. truma. Does the loss of the ability to eat תרומה truma
if he is the slave of a כהן, kohen, is that considered
to be something that he is losing out from which would compromise
the idea that being freed is a complete benefit? So let's take
a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabanan we
taught, this is about תניא tanya like we showed in our ברייתא
Baraita about 14 lines from the bottom. אמר רבי אלעזר: Amar Rabbi
Elazar: אמרנו לו למאיר, Amarnu lo l'Meir, we said to מאיר, Meir,
we the חכמים chachamim who said that it is a definite benefit
to the slave to be freed, we said to רבי מאיר: Rabbi
Meir: ולא זכותו היא לעבד שיצא מתחת יד רבו לחירות? v'lo zechuso
hi l'eved sheyeitzei mi-tachas yad rabo l'cheirus? It's an absolute benefit to
be freed, okay, so why can't somebody represent the slave? אמר לנו
חוב הוא
לו. Amar lanu chov hu lo. No, it's a detriment to him,
there is some area where it actually is a loss. What's the
area of a loss? שאם היה עבד כהן פוסל מן התרומה. she-im
haya eved kohen pasul min hatruma. At least in the case of
a slave of a כהן. kohen. What about the case of a
slave of ישראל? Yisrael? We'll discuss, but anyway in the case of
a slave of a כהן kohen there is some loss and therefore
it's not an absolute benefit and therefore you cannot automatically represent the
slave. What's the loss? That he will not be able to eat
תרומה. truma. The wife of a כהן kohen and the slave of
a כהן kohen can eat תרומה truma because the slave because it's
his property, the wife because it's marriage his household, and they will
lose that benefit. So there's always going to be some loss.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says there is always going to be a
loss, well at least in the case of a כהן kohen master.
אמרנו לו, Amarnu lo, we said back to רבי מאיר: Rabbi Meir:
ולו מאי מפסד שאינו חייב לזונו ולפרנסו רשאי. v'lo mai mafsed she-eino
chayav le-zono u-le-farneso rashai. But one minute, he doesn't have to feed
him. Now what does that have to do with the תרומה truma
point? So תוספות Tosafot says it seems like they understood the reason
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was saying תרומה truma is an issue is
because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was saying he'll get a lot of
food from his master because his master can give him תרומה truma
and therefore תרומה truma is cheaper so he'll give him a lot
of food. And they said back to him but there's no legal
obligation to feed him, so who cares about תרומה? truma? Why is
so where's the loss? אמר לנו, Amar lanu, he said back to
us: ומה אילו עבד כהן שברח ואשת כהן שמרדה על בעלה הלא
אוכלין בתרומה. u-mah ilu eved kohen shebarach v'eishes kohen shemarda al ba'ala
halo ochlin betruma.
No, because as long as the woman is still married going back
comparing it to the woman and the slave is still owned even
without the master they can eat תרומה. truma. Okay, so they don't
need the master to feed them. They could have run away and
they could still go collect תרומה truma from people, you know, in
the in the grain silos and the threshing floors and they can
go ahead and buy it in the market. So this is a
benefit that they have which is unrelated to the master's obligation to
free the slave. וזה אינו אוכל, v'zeh eino ochel, and once he's
freed he's losing out on this ability of access to תרומה. truma.
So there is a definite loss and therefore at least in the
case of a slave of a כהן kohen it is not an
absolute benefit and somebody you cannot say זכין. zachin. אבל אשה חוב
הוא לה שכן פוסלה מן התרומה ומפסדה מן המזונות. aval isha chov
hu lah she-ken posla min hatruma u-mefasda min hamzonos. The אבל aval
is interesting here, but certainly let's say by a woman it's to
her detriment. Number one is
she no longer the husband no longer has a legal obligation to
feed her and number two she can't eat תרומה. truma. So by
a woman she loses both of those things so it's not a
definite benefit to be divorced. And by a slave even though there's
no legal obligation to feed him he still loses his rights to
תרומה. truma. So that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's claim that there is
not an absolute benefit. So now the גמרא Gemara wants to understand
more, like get into this. מאי קאמרו ליה ומאי קמהדר ליה? Mai
ka-amru lei u-mai ka-mahadar lei? What did they say to him and
what did he respond? Let's like explain exactly this back and forth.
הכי קאמר להו: hachi ka-amar lehu: השבתונו על המזונות משיבו אנו על
התרומה. hasheivtunu al hamzonos mashivu anan al hatruma. So they said back
to him okay you said to us there's no legal obligation to
feed, fine, but you
know... He said to them, you have given me an answer that
there's no legal obligation to feed. I can see that by the
slave; there's no legal obligation to feed. But there's still a תרומה
terumah point independent of the legal obligation to feed the slave, and
you have not responded to that. Okay, וכי תימרו ve'chi teimru now
you'll say back to
me, אי בעי זריק ליה גיטא ופסיל ליה i ba'i zarik leh
gita u'pasil leh שביק ליה וערק ואזיל לעלמא, shavik lei ve'arak ve'azil
l'alma, so you'll say look, the fact that the כהן, kohen, that
the slave can eat תרומה, terumah, that is, you know, that is
not a, that doesn't make it a problem for somebody to represent
the slave to get the גט, get, because you don't need a
שליח shaliach to prevent the slave from eating תרומה. terumah. You can
divorce the slave, free the slave against his will, you can just
throw the גט get at him within his
ארבע אמות arba amot and he'll be free. So the fact that
somebody is choosing to represent him, you can't say oh you can't
do that because now he's going to lose out on the benefit
of תרומה. terumah. That is something the master could make happen regardless.
But the answer back is one
minute. שביק ליה וערק ואזיל לעלמא. shavik lei ve'arak ve'azil l'alma. No,
but you still need the slave or somebody representing him. The slave
could run away. That's why he gives the example of a slave
that ran away. So the slave could run away. So the master
cannot take away the ability of the slave to eat תרומה terumah
without the slave being present or his representative. So when you are
choosing to represent the slave, you are hurting the slave. You are
giving the master the ability to take away the opportunity for the
slave to eat תרומה. terumah. And that's why Rabbi Meir says I'm
always going to consider, or at least in the case of a
כהן, kohen, that there is some loss and you can't say זכין
zachin because that allows the master to take away the ability of
the slave to eat תרומה. terumah. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
then
what, ומה אלו עבד כהן שברח ואשת כהן שמרדה על בעלה הלא
אוכלין בתרומה וזה אינו אוכל? u'mah ilu eved kohen she'barach ve'eshet kohen
she'marda al ba'alah halo ochlin b'terumah ve'zeh einu ochel? So there you
go. There's a way this slave has the right to eat תרומה,
terumah, it has nothing to do with the master's obligation to feed
him. It has, the master cannot remove that from him without the
slave or his representative being present, and that is a loss. So
that's why you cannot say זכין, zachin, says Rabbi Meir. So the
גמרא Gemara says, שפיר קאמר להו, shapir k'amar lehu, so that was
a good response. So what, how did the rabbis respond
back? So אמר רבא amar Rava היינו דקא מהדרי ליה במתניתין hainu
d'ka mahadrei lei b'matnisin מפני שהוא קניינו. mipnei she'hu kinyano. So the
answer to that can be found in our
משנה: Mishnah: because the slave is owned by the master. Now how
does that respond to the effect that the slave is still losing
out in terms of this תרומה terumah issue? So let's take a
look. דאי בעי שקיל ארבע זוזי מישראל ופסלי ליה לכל היכא דאיתיה.
d'i ba'i shakil arba zuzei mi'Yisrael u'pasleh leh le'chol heicha d'iteih. Because
since he is owned by the master and the reason he eats
תרומה terumah is because he's the possession of a כהן, kohen, the
כהן kohen can always remove his ability to eat תרומה terumah without
the slave or his representative present. How? Just sell him to a
ישראל. Yisrael. Excuse me, to a Jew, to a ישראל, Yisrael, to
a non-כהן. kohen. So therefore, it is true, they seem to be
saying back, that there is a loss by losing תרומה, terumah, but
that does not prevent somebody from serving as a שליח, shaliach, because
that is something that can be taken away without anybody representing the
slave. It could be taken away by selling the slave to a
ישראל. Yisrael. And therefore when this person is choosing to represent the
slave, he is not hurting the slave in any way. The only
way you Rabbi Meir say he's hurting the slave has to do
with תרומה. terumah. That is not something that was dependent on him
choosing to represent the slave. That is something that could be taken
away from the slave even without anybody, without the slave or his
representative involved, just by selling him to a ישראל. Yisrael. Okay, so
that's the
debate. ולרבי מאיר, u'le'Rabbi Meir, now the גמרא Gemara says, according to
Rabbi Meir that says it's always some element of a
loss, תינח עבד כהן עבד ישראל מאי איכא למימר? tinei eved kohen
eved Yisrael mai ika le'meimar? So what about the slave of a
ישראל? Yisrael? Why shouldn't it work at least in that case? Where's
there a loss there? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי שמואל
בר רב יצחק amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak מפני שמפסידו משפחה
כנענית. mipnei she'mafsido mi'shifcha kena'anit. That he makes him lose out the
ability to have sex with a
non-Jewish maidservant, a non-Jewish female slave. Okay, so he is limiting his
sexual freedom, so there is some loss. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אדרבה adaraba הרי הוא מתיר לו בת חורין. harei hu matyir lo
bat chorin. Why is that a loss? You know, he doesn't have,
he can't have sex with female slaves, but now he can go
ahead and marry and have sex with a Jewish woman. So why
should we assume one is better than the other? You know, why
is that a loss? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, עבדא בהפקירא
ניחא ליה. avda b'hefkera nicha lei. The slave would rather have the
lack of any restrictions. So when you're not, when you're freed and
from going from an עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani to ישראל, Yisrael, so
now you have to abide by the הלכה halacha which requires marriage
and so on, and there's presumably also
just in terms of the mores an assumption that there is. more
sexual mores in place. So therefore he would rather be a slave
and have the type of sexual freedom and lack of mores than
he would in terms of than he would in terms of being
free. ניחא ליה דליהוי בהפקר וליהוי זילא ליה ושכיחא ליה ופריצא ליה.
Nicha lei d'lehvei b'hefkeir v'lehvei zila lei v'shchicha lei v'pritza lei. And
this speaks also something about the whole sort of, you know, social
and maybe power dynamics etc. So, you know, if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, זילא ליה, zila lei, she's like cheap in his eyes.
This is really horrific. Take a look at רש"י. Rashi. זולה היא
בעיניו ומזלזל בה לכל תאותו. Zola hi b'einav u'mezalzel ba l'chol ta'avaso.
You know, he's a slave, but she's also a slave and because
she's also a slave, he feels that he can just take sexual
advantage of her. Now if he means rape or, you know, who
knows what, but certainly does not treat her with due dignity and
respect, and she's very שכיחא ליה, shchicha lei, she's around all the
time, you know, it's an assumption. And פריצא ליה, pritza lei, and
she's willing and she also does not have sexual mores. So it's
a life of greater sexual freedom, lack of respect for women and
so on, and therefore we cannot assume that the slave wants this
change in status. Very fascinating having all of this perspective, you know,
told through the perspective of people that are not slaves and whatever,
you know, a lot more to say about that. Anyway, okay. So
that's the debate of whether it is a definite benefit to be
freed or are there some losses that the גמרא Gemara imagined in
terms of that, which is רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. Now we
move on to the next משנה. Mishnah. האומר תנו גט זה לאשתי
ושטר שחרור זה לעבדי, Ha'omer tnu get zeh l'ishti u'shtar shichrur zeh
l'avdi, somebody who says give this גט. get. Now there's a major
debate whether it has the word זה, zeh, because that suggests that
a גט get is being handed over and we've actually just discussed
a גט get being handed over where it sounds, you know, where
we were told about whether, you know, the implications of that. This
actually the, you know, it's debated, but we will choose to read
this without the word זה. zeh. Just give a גט get to
my wife, which is actually meaning that he is commanding it to
be written and given to his wife, or שטר שחרור זה לעבדי,
shtar shichrur zeh l'avdi, or this writ of manumission to my slave,
ומת, u'meis, and he dies, לא יתנו לאחר מיתה, lo yitnu l'achar
misah, and he dies, don't give after death. So again, if we're
talking about זה, zeh, something physically being handed over, then this would
be according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Because according to the חכמים,
Chachamim, as soon as the שטר שחרור shtar shichrur was handed over,
the slave would be freed. So either it's talking about זה zeh
and it's according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, or it's not talking
about זה, zeh, nothing is being handed
over, it's being sort of commanded to be written and given over,
and then the guy dies. So one way or another, after he's
dead, you cannot fulfill his commands, you cannot hand it over because
then, you know, the person, the slave automatically transfers to the heirs,
the woman automatically becomes an אלמנה. almanah. So therefore no longer can
that act be done. Okay. תנו מנה לפלוני ומת. Tnu maneh l'ploni
u'meis. However if somebody says give a hundred dollars to somebody and
then he dies, יתנו לאחר מיתה, yitnu l'achar misah, that you do
give after he dies. Now the question is why? Doesn't the property
transfer to the heirs? Why does his thing still take effect? So
we'll take a look in the גמרא. Gemara. By the way, the
parallel to the give the money also sounds like we're not talking
about money being handed over, so that would also argue to take
out the word זה zeh in the first part of the משנה.
Mishnah. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יצחק
בר שמואל בר מרתא משמיה דרב. Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar
Marta mishmei d'Rav. It says רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא Rav
Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta in the name of רב. Rav. והוא
שצבורים ומונחים בקרן זוית. V'hu she'tzvurim u'munachim b'keren zavis. The this thing
about the מנה, maneh, the hundred dollars works, if the hundred dollars
is all in a pile, it's a specifically designated, so almost like
a case of זה. zeh. Okay, but you know, there's a clear
thing that's being pointed to, if not handed over. So במאי עסקינן,
B'mai askinan, what's the case here? Why do you need to give
it those conditions? אילימא בברי, Ilima b'bari, the person saying give this
hundred dollars is a healthy person, so כי צבורין מאי הוי? Ki
tzurvin mai hovei? הלא משך? Hala meshach? Who cares that they're like
in a corner of his room and he says, you know, give
that hundred dollars to so and so? And then the guy drops
dead. Okay, so the person, nobody took possession of that money. The
receiver did not, the person he was telling to give it to
the receiver did not in the context of the זכין zachin question.
So why does that work? ואלא בשכיב מרע. V'ela b'shchiv mei'ra. We're
talking about a guy on his deathbed. And the הלכה halacha about
a guy on his deathbed is when he says give so and
so, it then it's like his words take automatic effect because we
want him to not get perturbed, you know, about his final wishes
that that would actually aggravate his situation and hasten his death. So
if that's true, מאי איריא צבורין? כי אין צבורין נמי. Mai irya
tzvurin? Ki ein tzvurin nami. Even if they weren't in a pile,
even if he was on his deathbed and just said give a
hundred dollars, that would automatically take effect. דקיימא לן דדברי שכיב מרע
ככתובים וכמסורים דמו. D'kayma lan d'divrei shchiv mei'ra k'chsuvim u'chm'surim damu. The
words of a שכיב מרע shchiv mei'ra are like they're already written
and handed over. It's like done and deal, signed, sealed and delivered.
So what is the idea of it being in this pile? Now
by the way you might ask, you know, why doesn't the גמרא
Gemara say that the reason you do it is not because the
transfer already took place, which is sort of what it's trying to
figure out here. How come by the money the it's like the
transfer took place, but by the גט get and the שטר שחרור
shtar shichrur not for the reasons we said. It sounds why not
just say it didn't take place, but there's a concept of מצוה
לקיים דברי המת mitzvah l'kayeim divrei ha'meis that when somebody says something
and then they die, there's a מצוה mitzvah to fulfill their wishes.
So תוספות Tosafot and רש"י Rashi discuss that. It's debated whether we
say it, even if we do
say it. at least that's something that's discussed there, is a concept
out there like that. But we are now assuming that actually what
the משנה mishnah means is that in the case of money it
actually took effect. The גט get and the שטר שחרור shtar shichrur
not because it needed to actually be received by the person or
by their שליח, shaliach, and but however by the money it did
take effect. So let's figure out why. So and why it needs
to be this pile. אמר אשי: Amar Ashi: לעולם ברי וכרב הונא.
le'olam bari u'kh'Rav Huna. We're talking about a ברי bari healthy person
and it's like going like
רב הונא. Rav Huna. אמר אמר רב, Amar amar Rav, דאמר רב
הונא אמר רב d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav and we remember this
statement earlier was in the name of רב Rav about that they're
in a pile. מנה לי בידך תנהו לפלוני במעמד שלשתן קנה. Maneh
li b'yadcha teneyhu l'ploni b'maamad shloshtan kanah.
So ראובן Reuven says to שמעון: Shimon: שמעון, Shimon, you owe me
a hundred dollars, instead of giving it to me, give it to
לוי. Levi. Because I owe לוי Levi a hundred dollars or I
want לוי Levi just to have it as a gift. So automatically
now שמעון Shimon that automatically takes effect. שמעון Shimon no longer owes
me the hundred dollars, he now owes it to לוי. Levi. And
if שמעון Shimon had a, you know, an actual hundred dollar bill
of mine in his, you know, in his possession or like a
laptop computer and I said that laptop computer that you're watching for
me, that you're holding for me, give it to לוי, Levi, then
automatically it now belongs to לוי. Levi. That's called מעמד שלשתן. maamad
shloshtan. All three of them are around and you say give it
to him, it takes immediate effect. And we're going to see why
that is. So רב פפא אמר: Rav Pappa amar: Now, we have
not yet said why it needs to be in a pile. What
the גמרא Gemara is going to say is, is and I alluded
to in the laptop example is that this idea of does it
take effect is debated whether it applies by a loan or only
by a פקדון, pikadon, a concrete object. So according to this approach,
רב Rav only said it in the case of a concrete object.
So if you've got that pile of money and now presumably actually
means the צבורין ומונחין, tziburin u'munachin, it's not exactly clear before whose
property it was צבורין ומונחין tziburin u'munachin in. But now if this
property is צבורין ומונחין, tziburin u'munachin, if this money was in the
property of שמעון, Shimon, and the guy said: שמעון, Shimon, give that
hundred dollars to לוי, Levi, and then he dropped dead, it works
because of the principle of מעמד שלשתן. maamad shloshtan. But if it
was not a concrete object and it was just give money that
you owe me, it would not work. So answer number one is:
Why does it work in the משנה mishnah that the money transfers
and not the גט get and the שטר שחרור? shtar shichrur? Because
we're talking about this principle called מעמד שלשתן, maamad shloshtan, which works
when you're talking with concrete objects, צבורין ומונחין tziburin u'munachin in שמעון's
Shimon possession and therefore it automatically transfers to לוי. Levi. Okay, that
works for money, it does not work for the שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur and for the גט. get. That's one explanation. By the way
I should say that if it's already in שמעון's Shimon possession, you
could say it works because of the principle of זכין. zachin. That
שמעון's Shimon property takes possession for it on behalf of לוי, Levi,
so it's not exactly clear why we needed the principle of מעמד
שלשתן. maamad shloshtan. תוספות Tosfos says, you know, מעמד שלשתן maamad shloshtan
could work even against שמעון's Shimon desire. שמעון Shimon even if שמעון
Shimon says: No, I don't want to do that. I don't want
to transfer it to לוי. Levi. So in that case, if you
had to use the principle of זכין zachin it would not work.
But because of the principle of מעמד שלשתן, maamad shloshtan, when they're
all present, that can be done against even if שמעון Shimon doesn't
like it, and that's the case that we're reading into the משנה.
mishnah. Okay? So once again, the גט get and the שטר שחרור
shtar shichrur don't work, either because you don't say זכין zachin by
them like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, or you don't say זכין zachin
by either, or we're not talking about something physically being handed over.
Money does work, and according to one statement it only works when
it's in a pile. Why? Because of the principle of מעמד שלשתן.
maamad shloshtan. It's in a pile and it's a physical object and
it's in שמעון's Shimon possession and therefore it can be transferred to
לוי. Levi. Okay, so that's a case of
ברי. bari. Now, רב פפא אמר: Rav Pappa amar: לעולם בשכיב מרע
le'olam b'shchiv mei'ra וכאידך דרב. u'kh'idach d'Rav. And it's going like the
other statement of רב, Rav, right? Because if it's a שכיב מרע,
shchiv mei'ra, even if it wasn't in a pile. שכיב מרע shchiv
mei'ra says something, automatically takes effect. So why did רב Rav say
it had to be in a pile? דאמר רב שכיב מרע שאמר
תנו מנה לפלוני
מנכסי. d'amar Rav shchiv mei'ra she'amar tenu maneh l'ploni mi'nechasai. So let's
say a שכיב מרע shchiv mei'ra said: give so and so a
hundred dollars from my, you know, of my property. מנה זה נותנין.
maneh zeh nosnim. If he said specifically which hundred dollars, you know,
give him the hundred dollars in that drawer, okay, you would give
it. מנה סתם אין נותנין. maneh stam ein nosnim. Give him a
hundred dollars from my property, you don't give. Why? חיישינן שמא מנה
קבור קאמר. chashinan shema maneh kavur ka'amar. Because we don't know which
hundred dollars he meant, and therefore maybe he meant a hundred dollars
that he had buried in some hole that we don't know about.
So this person doesn't have any claim on any particular hundred dollars.
Now, it's a little funny because you would think that if somebody
says give him a hundred dollars from my estate, you're talking about
the abstract sense of a hundred dollars, you know, just from the
proceeds of my estate. So תוספות Tosfos tries to figure out exactly
what the parameters are when it's clear that you mean the proceeds,
obviously you would, but here anyway there was some sense because of
certain contexts I won't go into the
specifics. So since you meant something concrete and you don't say which
thing you're talking about, then you don't have to give him anything.
So therefore, that's why, since רב *Rav* says that, we're going to
read the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* in that way. Again, why we don't
just read the משנה *Mishna* to say give him a hundred dollars
from the proceeds
is not clear, but okay, that's already something taught in בבא בתרא
*Bava Basra*, the idea of דברי שכיב מרע shchiv mera *divrei sh'chiv
mera*. This is talking about something else, that he's speaking about giving
a specific hundred dollars, but he and that will work in the
principle of דברי שכיב מרע shchiv mera *divrei sh'chiv mera* if you
know which specific hundred dollars he's talking about, and that's what ציבורין
ומונחין *tziburin u'munachin* means. If you know which specific hundred dollars he's
talking about it works; if he says a concrete hundred dollars but
doesn't say which, then it doesn't work. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says והלכתא לקבור לא חיישינן *v'hilchasa l'kavor lo chaishinan*, but as
a matter of practical הלכה halakhah *halacha*, that's a little extreme and
we're not concerned about it. Okay, two ways to read the משנה
*Mishna* now about the money, again, the גט *get* and the שטר
שחרור *shtar shichrur*, you don't say זוכין *zochin*. The money works either
because it's a ברי *bari* and he's transferring it based on מעמד
שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan *ma'amad shloshtan* and all three are present and it's
a concrete object. Okay, or it works because he's a שכיב מרע
*sh'chiv mera* and then in theory you really don't need anything concrete
and specific, but if you're concerned about this buried money then you
might need it to be concrete and specific. רב פפא *Rav Pappa*,
okay, now רב פפא מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב זביד *Rav Pappa
mai ta'ama lo amar k'Rav Zevid*? Why did רב פפא *Rav Pappa*
not say like רב זביד *Rav Zevid* that it's based on this
מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan *ma'amad shloshtan* idea?
So קסבר רב פפא *kasavar Rav Pappa*, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* is
of the position כי אמר רב לא שנא במלווה ולא שנא בפיקדון
*ki amar Rav lo shena b'milveh v'lo shena b'pikadon*. This idea of
מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan *ma'amad shloshtan*, it's not limited to a case
of a concrete object; it's true even about a loan. שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* owes me a hundred dollars, I say שמעון Shimon *Shimon* give
that hundred dollars to לוי Levi. *Levi*, boom, now you owe it
to לוי Levi *Levi*. Okay, so therefore he doesn't want to say
when רב *Rav* demanded it be in a pile and concrete we're
talking about מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan *ma'amad shloshtan*. He doesn't think that
רב *Rav* requires that for מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan *ma'amad shloshtan*. רב
זביד מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב פפא *Rav Zevid mai ta'ama lo
amar k'Rav Pappa*? Now why did רב זביד *Rav Zevid* not say
like רב פפא *Rav Pappa* that we're talking about a שכיב מרע
*sh'chiv mera* and the issue of having to be concrete is a
concern that רב'ס *Rav's* concerned about a buried money? So he says
לא מיתוקמא מתניתין בשכיב מרע *lo misukma masnisin b'sh'chiv mera*. No, the
משנה *Mishna* doesn't, it doesn't sound to me that the משנה *Mishna*
is talking at all about a שכיב מרע *sh'chiv mera* that we
should introduce that idea in the משנה *Mishna*, that the guy's on
his deathbed. ממאי *mimai*? How do you know that? מדקתני האומר תנו
גט זה לאשתי ושטר שחרור זה לעבדי ומת לא יתנו לאחר מיתה
*midekatni ha'omer tenu get zeh l'ishti u'shtar shichrur zeh l'avdi u'meis lo
yitnu l'achar misa*. Because it says, going back to the first part,
the guy's trying to divorce his wife or give a שטר שחרור
*shtar shichrur* to his slave, don't give it after he dies. So
טעמא דמת *ta'ama demis*, so the משנה'ס *Mishna's* clear that the reason
you're not giving it is because the guy's dead. הא מחיים *ha
mechayim*, if he was alive, נותנין *nosnin*, you would give it. טעמא
דאמר תנו *ta'ama d'amar tenu*, and the reason that it would seem
that you would be prepared to give it if he were still
alive was because he said תנו *tenu*. הא לא אמר תנו אין
נותנין *ha lo amar tenu ein nosnin*. Let's say he didn't say
תנו *tenu*, let's say he just said write a גט *get* for
my wife, write a שטר שחרור *shtar shichrur* for my slave, so
it would seem like you wouldn't give it. Okay, the משנה *Mishna*
seems to say the guy said תנו *tenu*, you would give it
as long as he was alive, but not once he's dead, and
the implication being because he said תנו *tenu* you would give it.
If he said something less than תנו *tenu*, like write a גט
*get*, then you would write it but you wouldn't deliver it. Okay,
that's implied he thinks in the משנה *Mishna*, and now he's saying
but that's not true by a שכיב מרע *sh'chiv mera*. By שכיב
מרע *sh'chiv mera*, because the guy fears he's about to die, when
he says write a גט *get*, we assume write means write it
and give it. Okay, ושכיב מרע אף על גב דלא אמר תנו
נותנין *u'sh'chiv mera af al gav d'lo amar tenu nosnin*. By שכיב
מרע *sh'chiv mera*, even if he didn't say תנו *tenu*, you would
give it, even if he just said כתבו *kisvu*. דתנן *detnan*, we
taught in the משנה *Mishna*, בראשונה היו אומרים היוצא בקולר *barishona hayu
omrim hayotzei b'kolar*. Somebody who was being taken out in like chains
and he was going to be executed, ואמר כתבו גט לאשתי *v'amar
kisvu get l'ishti*, write a גט *get* for my wife because he
didn't want her to have to worry about יבום *yibum*. Okay, so
he didn't, he wanted her to be better off being divorced than
being widowed. Okay, כתבו גט לאשתי *kisvu get l'ishti*, הרי זה יכתב
ויתנו *harei zeh yikaseiv v'yitnu*. You assume write means write it and
give it. You can't give it without the husband appointing somebody a
שליח *shaliach* to give it, but in this context the word write
means write it and deliver it. חזרו לומר *chazru lomar*, then they
added to the, they went back and said, אף המפרש והיוצא בשיירה
*af hamifaresh v'hayotzei b'shayara*, even somebody who is going out on a
sea journey or on a caravan afraid he might not come back
alive, also, you're rushed and you're distracted, so you would say כתבו
*kisvu*, but you really meant כתבו תנו *kisvu tenu*. Okay, so those
are cases we interpret the word כתבו *kisvu* to mean not only
write it but write it and give it. ורבי שמעון Shimon שזורי
אומר *v'Rabbi Shimon Shezuri omer*, רבי שמעון Shimon שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri*
says אף המסוכן *af hamesukan*, even somebody that is in danger of
dying, meaning somebody on his deathbed. Okay, so therefore he says here's
why I don't like reading the משנה *Mishna* by שכיב מרע *sh'chiv
mera*, because if it was a שכיב מרע *sh'chiv mera*, then the
first, then the suggestion in the משנה *Mishna* is that you deliver
the גט *get* if the guy is still alive because he said
תנו *tenu*, but less than that you wouldn't, and by שכיב מרע
*sh'chiv mera*, even if you just said כתבו *kisvu*, you would deliver
the גט *get*. Now that's a lot of assumptions to read in,
so let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers. מתקיף לה רב
אשי Rav Ashi, *maskif lah Rav Ashi*, רב אשי *Rav Ashi* challenges
this problem, וממאי דמתניתין רבי שמעון Shimon שזורי היא דילמא רבנן היא
*u'mimai d'masnisin Rabbi Shimon Shezuri hee dilma rabbanan hee*? That shouldn't prevent
you. Why do you have to assume the משנה *Mishna* is רבי
שמעון Shimon שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri*? The משנה *Mishna* could be the
רבנן *rabbanan*. It was only רבי שמעון Shimon שזורי *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri*
that said the כתבו *kisvu* of a שכיב מרע *sh'chiv mera* means
write it and give it. Anyway, but so now here's what we
have. When he says give a get to my wife, you don't
give it once he's dead and you don't say זכין. When he
says give the hundred dollars, you do give it after he dies,
either because of מעמד שלשתן ma'amad shloshtan and that would be whether
it is if Rav requires מעמד שלשתן ma'amad sheloshtan. to be פיקדון,
pikadon, then it's talking about that the stuff is a concrete
פיקדון pikadon being guarded, held by the other person, a specific object.
And if Rav says that even by a מלווה milveh then it
would apply by a מלווה. milveh. Or the משנה is talking about
a שכיב מרע and that's why it works because what a שכיב
מרע says is binding and then again, if Rav, if there's a
concern about a hidden מנה, maneh, we would be talking about the
fact that this hundred dollars was concrete and obvious what we were
talking about. All right, גופא. Gufa. Let's now take a breath and
go back to this principle of מעמד שלשתן and explore it on
its own terms. אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Huna amar
Rav, מנה לי בידך, maneh li b'yadcha, you owe me a hundred
dollars, תנהו לו לפלוני tnehu lo l'ploni במעמד שלשתן, b'ma'amad shloshtan, if
all three of them are present, קנה, kanah, then Levi now is
the one that owns the hundred dollars.
אמר רבא מסתברא מילתא דרב בפיקדון. Amar Rava mistabra milta d'Rav b'pikadon.
Rava says this makes sense by a פיקדון pikadon because then it's
like a very specific concrete thing and it's if I transferred it
over to the other person. Again, if Shimon was agreeing, you wouldn't
even need מעמד שלשתן because Shimon's property could just be seen as
taking possession of it for Levi. Maybe it's not always directly in
Shimon's property, but anyway, but מעמד שלשתן works therefore even according to
Tosafot even if Shimon doesn't agree, even if it's not in his
property, but you understand the logic, there's like a mechanism there that
it could transfer it to Levi. Okay, so that's by a פיקדון.
pikadon. אבל במלווה לא, Aval b'milveh lo, but not by a debt.
A debt is abstract, it's just debt, Shimon owes me money. How
does all of a sudden now Shimon owe Levi money because I
said it? So the גמרא Gemara responds back, והא לאו הכי, v'ha
lav hachi, is that really true? In God's name, אמר רבא אפילו
במלווה. amar Rava afilu b'milveh. No, Rava said it even by a
debt. איתמר נמי אמר שמואל משמיה דלוי, Itmar nami amar Shmuel mishmei
d'Levi, מנה לי בידך, maneh li b'yadcha, you owe me a hundred
dollars as a debt, תנהו לו לפלוני tnehu lo l'ploni במעמד שלשתן,
b'ma'amad shloshtan, and give it now to Levi and if they're all
three present, קנה, kanah, now Levi owns the money or the money
is owed to Levi. Okay, so you see that this idea of
מעמד שלשתן goes, those that say it works, say that it works
even in the case of a debt. If that's true, וטעמא מאי,
v'ta'ama mai, what's the reason behind this? Like how does that work?
So the וטעמא מאי v'ta'ama mai could be two questions, one is
what motivated it and the other is what is the legal mechanism.
So אמר אמימר amar Amemar says Amemar, נעשה כאומר לו בשעת מתן
מעות, na'aseh k'omer lo b'sha'at matan ma'ot, it's as if when Shimon,
I lent Shimon the money, it's as if when Shimon by agreeing
to take my hundred dollars and owe me the money, it's as
if he said to me when I handed him the money, שעבדנא
לך ולדידך ולכל דאתו מחמתך. shibadna lach u'l'didach u'l'chol d'asu machmatchach. I
am obligating myself to you, putting a lien on myself, subjugating myself,
obligating myself to you to pay the hundred dollars and to anyone
who comes on your account, any of your designees. So implicitly
when Shimon took my money, he agreed to pay it back to
me or to anyone whom I would designate. Okay, now it's as
if he said that. He didn't really say that, he just borrowed
the money. But חז"ל, Chazal, whatever motivated them for this mechanism, there's
a question about why did they want to create the mechanism, but
the mechanism is we view it as if Shimon has agreed to
owe it to anybody who I would designate. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר ליה רב אשי לאמימר. amar lei Rav Ashi l'Amemar.
So Rav Ashi said to Amemar, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, one minute,
but that would only work if the person Levi was alive when
Shimon borrowed the money. Then Shimon could say by taking this money
I'm obligating myself to you or to whoever else it might turn
out that you designate. And then if in the end I designate
Levi, well since Levi was alive at the time, ten years ago
when he borrowed the money, then it's like Shimon ten years ago
said I'll owe the money to Levi. But if Levi was only
born after he borrowed the money, then where is Shimon obligating himself
to Levi? How can he obligate himself to me ten years ago
to someone who doesn't yet exist? Right now if we're ten years
ago at the ten years time, he could say I accept an
obligation to pay you and to pay whomever else you right now
designate and I'm assuming that obligation now. But if it's somebody that
isn't alive now, I can't obligate myself now to somebody in the
future. If I want to be obligated to a somebody born in
the future, I have to be obligate myself to them only once
they were alive. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says, if
Levi is born afterwards. The obligation that שמעון Shimon's undertook ten years
ago cannot have applied to לוי. Levi Why? דאפילו לרבי מאיר דאמר
אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, da'afilu le-Rabbi Meir de-amar adam makneh
davar she-lo ba le-olam, even according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that
says that you can transfer, like sell something that doesn't yet exist.
I will sell you the fruit of this tree once they come
into existence. הני מילי לדבר שישנו בעולם. hani mili ledavar sheyeshno ba'olam.
That's when you are giving it to someone who exists. It's the
object that doesn't yet exist. אבל לדבר שאינו בעולם לא, aval ledavar
she'eino ba'olam lo, but you cannot transfer something now to a person
who is not yet alive. So שמעון Shimon ten years ago cannot
have obligated himself to לוי Levi. who wasn't alive then. All right?
So how does this work if it's based on when שמעון Shimon
borrowed the money? It's like he obligated himself to whoever he was
going to say, blah blah blah, that cannot have worked, that thing
ten years ago cannot have worked to somebody who was born only
after the fact. אלא אמר רב אשי, ela amar Rav Ashi, says
רב אשי, בההיא הנאה דקא משתניא ליה בין מלווה ישנה למלווה חדשה
גמר ומשעבד נפשיה. be-hai hana'ah de-ka mishtanya lei bein milveh yeshanah le-milveh
chadashah gamar u-meshabeid nafsheih.
You're right. Since we have to include cases where לוי Levi was
born later, we have to say that right now when I'm doing
the transfer, שמעון is obligating himself to לוי. Levi? Okay? What's the
mechanism of that? Right? You can't ascribe it to what happened ten
years ago, it has to be now because לוי Levi is only,
was born like recently. Okay? So what is the mechanism where now
the loan becomes obligated to לוי? Levi. So the גמרא says, well
look, שמעון is benefiting in this exchange, because he's owed me the
money for ten years. He's in deep arrears. He'd rather it be
a new loan with לוי Levi. which will give him a little
bit of a breather, you know, and not feel the same pressure
to pay it up right away. And since he benefits from it
being created as a new loan, that benefit—in order to obligate yourself
you have to receive something, right?—so in exchange for that benefit, that
created the conviction to obligate himself now to לוי. Again, שמעון is
not saying this necessarily, but this is what we're reading in. This
is the virtual mechanism that is allowing it to transfer. So the
גמרא says, אמר ליה הונא מר בריה דרב נחמיה לרב אשי, amar
lei Huna Mar brei de-Rav Nechemya le-Rav Ashi, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata,
if that's the logic that he benefits, that שמעון benefits, כגון הני
דבי בר אלישיב, ke-gon hani de-bei Bar Elyashiv, let's say you were
transferring the loan to this house of the, you know, members of
this אלישיב Elyashiv household, okay, like the Corleones or something, דכפתי ושקלי
לאלתר, de-kaftei ve-shaklei le-altar, they bind people up and they take the
money right away. Okay? It's very nice it's a new loan, but
actually they're much worse, you know, they're going to send their goons
after you. So would we say it doesn't work? So how is
it going to work? הכא נמי דלא קנו? hacha nami de-lo kanu?
Would you say it doesn't work? וכי תימא הכא נמי? ve-khei teima
hacha nami? Yeah, that's true. אם כן נתת דבריך לשיעורין. im ken
natata devarekha le-shiyurin.
Then this is a mechanism that doesn't always work and we're going
to have to always assess case by case whether the person is
benefiting from it transferring to this new party. אלא אמר מר זוטרא,
ela amar Mar Zutra, הני תלת מילי שוינהו רבנן כהלכתא בלא טעמא.
hani telat milei shavinu rabanan ke-hilkheta belo ta'ama.
There are three things that the Rabbis did as a הלכה without
a reason. And they're going to say—and the three of them are
going to include מעמד שלשתן. We'll pick up with this tomorrow.
But the בלא טעמא belo ta'ama here does not mean there was
not a motivation. The בלא טעמא belo ta'ama means without really a
justifiable mechanism. Okay? So you're right. The mechanism here doesn't work. If
we're dealing with a פקדון, pikadon, the mechanism is easier because in
a lot of cases it's in שמעון property and שמעון agrees, so
his property takes possession for לוי. So even when those aren't true,
we can sort of at least we see the makings of a
mechanism. But in the case of a loan, if we extend it
to that, which it seems that's the agreement, right? Then the mechanism
isn't clear. It can't be that שמעון obligated himself at that time
to future people, because those people might not have existed yet. And
it can't be he obligates himself now to those people because he
might not have had a reason to obligate himself to those people.
So it's going to be—we're going to do it even without a
clearly defined mechanism and we will pick up with this tomorrow.